Finding Aid for Dept. of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (University of Michigan) records, 1919-1993.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Medical Center Alumni Society
  - Annual Giving Program 1972-1973 (Box 8)
  - Reunions 1969 (Box 8)
  - Alumni Program Talk September 26, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Reunions 1970-1974, 5 folders (Box 8)
- Medical Center House Officer Committee (MCHOC)
  The Medical Center House Officer Committee (MCHOC) series contains minutes and drafts of the negotiated contracts signed between the interns and residents comprising the house officer staff and the University of Michigan. Arranged chronologically by academic year, these files also include statistics on staffing allotments and requirements. Specific information on house officer arrangements at affiliated hospitals can be found under each respective hospital in the affiliated hospitals series. The MCHOC was folded into the Graduate Medical Education Committee beginning in 1990.
  - Minutes and Supporting Documentation 1971-1992, 15 folders (Box 9)
- Medical Television Committee
  Files of the Medical Television Committee richly document the development and use of television in medical instruction. The files, dating from 1953 to 1965, contain minutes and correspondence relating to some of the earliest uses of television technology in the field of medicine. This committee provides background on the Biomedical Communications unit administratively located within the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education. Of interest are program notes (1959-1962) which give a brief synopsis of each televised medical procedure or program, including personnel and equipment used in the program.
  - Television Committee, 1953-1964/65, 12 folders
    - Armed Forces Institute of Pathology (Symposium on Television in Medicine) 1955 (Box 10)
    - Bird, Edward (Television Project Officer National Naval Medical Center) 1959-1960 (Box 10)
    - Council on Medical Television 1959-1961 (Box 10)
    - Dow Foundation 1955-1965 (Box 10)
    - Directors Reports/Program Notes 1959-1962, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Faculty Demonstration 1958 (Box 10)
    - Judge, Dr. Richard (Inter-Office) 1959-1962 (Box 10)
    - Letters on Medical Television Programs 1955-1956 (Box 10)
    - Ruhe, Dave 1956-1962 (Box 10)
    - Television as A Visual Aid (Typescript Article) undated (Box 10)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (.5 linear feet) contains information about the department as a whole. Included are annual reports, curriculum committee minutes and information about grants and grant-funded projects. The series spans the years 1947-1973.
  - Annual Progress Letters, 1962/1963-1964/1965 (Box 12)
  - Conference on Graduate and Postgraduate Medical Education 1947 (Box 12)
  - Counseling 1958-1959 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence about Postgraduate Program 1956-1962 (Box 12)
  - Curriculum Committee 1956 (Box 12)
  - Grants
    - Coronary Care Project 1971-1972 (Box 12)
    - Medical Care Project 1972-1973 (Box 12)
  - Intern Questionnaire Summaries 1953-1956, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Kresge Medical Research Building 1951-1953 (Box 12)
  - Reports
    - Postgraduate Medicine Annual Report 1960-1961 (Box 12)
    - Enrollment and Teaching 1962-1967 (Box 12)
    - Five Year Interval Report 1960-1961 (Box 12)
    - Five Year Report to Medical School 1960 (Box 12)
    - Plan for Postgraduate Medical Education 1957 (Box 12)
    - Plan for Two Year General Residency 1947-1948 (Box 12)
  - Special Purpose Training Program 1971 (Box 12)
  - Towsley Center 1968-1971 (Box 12)
- Affiliated Hospitals
  The Affiliated Hospitals series (2.6 linear feet) is divided into six subseries: Administrative, Affiliated Hospital Days, Annual Reviews, Basic Science, Budgets, and Correspondence. Administrative contains reports and correspondence dealing with the various internship programs within the affiliated hospital program, particularly the general practice internship program. Annual reviews contains material relating to the visits of department staff to evaluate the affiliated hospitals in the mid 1960s. Basic Science documents some of the programs offered by the department in the 1940s and 1950s. Schedules and evaluations of the programs are included. Budgets contain financial information for the affiliated hospital program from 1947/48 to1954/55. Correspondence is divided into two parts. First is the correspondence, arranged by hospital, between the department and the affiliated hospitals. General correspondence is between the department and people or organizations not directly connected with an affiliated hospital. In both parts, Harry Towsley is the chief correspondent from the department. The series dates from 1947 to 1973.
  - Administrative
    - Affiliated Hospital Residency Training Program Annual Report, 1952/1953-1953/1954, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Clippings 1947-1948 (Box 12)
    - Decentralized Resident Training Program
      - Annual Reports
        - 1947-1948 (Box 12)
        - 1953/1954-1954/1955, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Evaluation of Residents
      - 1963/1964 (Box 11)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2039 ]
      - 1964/1965 (Box 11)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2040 ]
    - General Information 1948 (Box 12)
    - General Practice Internship Program
      - Annual Report 1951-1952 (Box 12)
      - Applications, 1949/1950 (Box 11)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
      - Correspondence 1947-1948 (Box 12)
    - General Practice Internship Program
      - General Practice Committee 1956 (Box 12)
      - Inquiries 1948-1951, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Internship Information 1958 (Box 12)
    - Intern Matching 1959-1964 (Box 12)
    - Letters of Recommendation 1950 (Box 11)
    - Office of Extramural Education 1972-1973 (Box 12)
    - Visiting Program 1964-1965 (Box 12)
  - Affiliated Hospital Day
    - 1960 (Box 12)
    - 1963-1965, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Annual Reviews
    - 1948-1949 (Box 13)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 13)
    - 1951 (Box 13)
    - Blodgett Memorial Hospital
      - 1953-1954 (Box 13)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Bronson Methodist Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Butterworth Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Hackley Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Hurley Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Leila Montgomery Hospital 1953-1954 (Box 13)
    - McLaren General Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Midland General Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Mount Carmel Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Munson Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Pontiac General Hospital 1961-1965 (Box 13)
    - Saginaw General Hospital 1961-1965 (Box 13)
    - St. Joseph Ann Arbor 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - St. Joseph Detroit 1964-1965 (Box 13)
    - St. Joseph Pontiac 1961-1965 (Box 13)
    - St. Lawrence Hospital 1961-1965 (Box 13)
    - St. Mary Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 13)
  - Basic Science
    - Applications (Box 11)
    - 1963/1964
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2049 ]
      - 1964/1965 (Box 11)
    - Comments on Students, 1963/1964 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1951 (Box 13)
    - Evaluations
      - 1947/1948-1948/1949, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - 1949/1950-1950/1951, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Schedules
      - 1947/1948-1950/1951, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 14)
      - 1959/1960-1963/1964, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Budget
    - 1947/1948-1954/1955, 7 folders (Box 14)
  - Correspondence (arranged by Hospital)
    - Alexander Bain Hospital 1953-1963 (Box 14)
    - Beyer Memorial Hospital 1949-1950 (Box 14)
    - Bixby Hospital 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Blodgett Memorial Hospital 1959-1965 (Box 14)
    - Bronson Methodist Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - Butterworth Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - East Deaconess 1954 (Box 14)
    - Hackley Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 14)
    - Harper Hospital 1949 (Box 14)
    - Hurley Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - Munson Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - McLaren General Hospital 1963-1965 (Box 14)
    - Mercy Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - Midland Hospital 1953-1955 (Box 14)
    - Mt. Carmel Mercy 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - Pontiac General Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - Saginaw General Hospital 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - St. Joseph Ann Arbor 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - St. Joseph Detroit 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - St. Joseph Pontiac 1963-1965 (Box 14)
    - St. Lawrence 1953-1964 (Box 14)
    - St. Mary's 1953-1965 (Box 14)
    - Sparrow Hospital 1949-1965 (Box 14)
    - VA Hospital Saginaw 1963 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence (general)
    - American Academy of Pediatrics 1960 (Box 15)
    - American Medical Association 1949-1950 (Box 15)
    - Coldwater Health Department 1946-1947 (Box 15)
    - Coller, F.A. 1949-1950 (Box 15)
    - Furstenburg, Albert 1949-1951 (Box 15)
    - Hospitals under consideration 1950-1951 (Box 15)
    - Juliar, Benjamin 1964 (Box 15)
    - Kellogg Foundation 1949 (Box 15)
    - Miller, Norman 1950 (Box 15)
    - Sturgis, Cyrus 1949-1950 (Box 15)
    - Towsley, Harry (incoming) 1951 (Box 15)
- Medical Center Journal
  The Medical Center Journal series contains correspondence and minutes of the editorial board when the Journal was edited by the Department of Postgraduate Medicine. The dates of this series are 1963-1975.
  - 1963-1975, 2 folders (Box 15)
- Medical Television Committee
  The Medical Television Committee series augments material found in the previous accession. The committee, also known as the Audiovisual Committee, tried to develop ways in which communications technology, television in particular, could further continuing medical education. Some photographs of early television equipment are included. The series spans the years 1953-1974.
  - "An Experiment in the Use of Closed Circuit Color Television for Postgraduate Medical Education: A Pilot Study," 1960 (Box 15)
  - "Cavity, Speculum, and Small Field TV," 1958 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence
    - Castle, Hamon 1959-1960 (Box 15)
    - Mackenzie, John 1960-1961 (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1959-1960 (Box 15)
      - 1964 (Box 15)
    - Remley, Fred 1961 (Box 15)
    - Trubey, R. 1960 (Box 15)
    - Tuxen, Neils 1960 (Box 15)
    - Vanselow, Neal and J. Turcotte 1963-1964 (Box 15)
    - Warner, Robert 1958 (Box 15)
    - Wolfe, D.E. 1960 (Box 15)
  - Media Library 1972-1974 (Box 15)
  - Network for Continuing Medical Education 1967-1968 (Box 15)
  - Photographs undated (Box 15)
  - Printed Material
    - 1956-1958 (Box 15)
  - Program Evaluations 1958-1962 (Box 15)
  - Reports
    - Beaumont Dedication 1954 (Box 15)
    - Color Television-American Medical Television Workshop 1955 (Box 15)
    - How to Use Television in the Health Field 1955 (Box 15)
    - Postgraduate Television Clinics 1953 (Box 15)
- James D. Bruce
  The James D. Bruce series contains speeches given by Dr. Bruce, who served as the first chairman of the department from 1927 to 1942. The speeches were given between 1919 and 1938 at a number of locations and events throughout Michigan and the nation. The speeches provide insight into the state of medical education and postgraduate medical education in particular in the 1920s and 1930s. Each folder in the series has its own index telling where and when most speeches were given.
  - Speeches
    - 1919-1937 (Box 15)
    - 1927-1938 (Box 15)
    - 1929-1936 (Box 15)
    - 1931-1939 (Box 15)
    - 1938 (Box 15)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 15)
Related Material
The James D. Bruce series contains speeches given by Dr. Bruce, who served as the first chairman of the department from 1927 to 1942. The speeches were given between 1919 and 1938 at a number of locations and events throughout Michigan and the nation. The speeches provide insight into the state of medical education and postgraduate medical education in particular in the 1920s and 1930s. Each folder in the series has its own index telling where and when most speeches were given.